After having made the commitment to
training in the eight precepts as
recommended by the Buddha, I do see
myself failing and making mistakes.
When this happens, my mind gets at me. I
feel remorse about my shortcomings, and
the only way out that I know of is to
fall back into behavior that is against
the precepts or against other values
that I uphold.
Shall I give in to what my mind
suggests, loosen up the moral
constraints I put myself under, or is
there another way to resolve this
internal struggle that is in line with
the Buddhist teaching?
>> Well, if if you feel remorse
for what you did,
then why would you
um randomly decide not to feel remorse
for doing it again? That's where
That's where
it it is a common line of thinking, but
if you examine it closely, you realize
it doesn't make sense. Cuz if you feel
remorseful for doing something, then surely you
for doing something, then surely you
would be you would
feel more remorseful for doing it more.
So, just maintain the perception of
shame in regard to that same action,
uh and recognize that well, it's going
to feel unpleasant that you failed,
but if you actually
if you actually
stay in line and don't abandon the
determination you don't intentionally
throw away the determination you
initially made,
uh you will automatically not want to do
it more
because it it feels shameful.
>> But I let's say I gave in in the first
place because I couldn't bear the
unpleasantness of my mind pressuring me.
>> Yeah, so then still feel ashamed. Like
feel ashamed that so you failed uh the
first time, you failed the second time,
well, feel even more ashamed of failing
the third time. And you will be. Like,
the problem is that you kind of or or
you people usually would feel like um
I don't want to feel
the burden of
feeling even more like a failure.
So, I just move the goalpost.
And then I
give up on the goal to begin with. But
no, if you keep it,
then the more you fail,
the bad the worse you will feel.
And that's the whole point.
Like, at some point it will have to happen
at some point it will have to happen
that
um
if you kept the goal
and you kept failing at it,
the the pain will get strong enough for
you to
you know,
uh at least determine
not to do it.
And then
you might fail again, which is expected.
But the thing is,
what you're training yourself is not for
the pressure to act not to come up in
the first place.
You're training yourself for the shame
to be stronger than the pressure to act.
So, that's why it's essential that you
don't um
uh move the goalpost and and and think
that like um
well, it's only really it only really
counts when I have like a perfect
stretch where
where
immediately upon deciding that I would
abstain, I successfully abstained.
No, that that can happen for many uh
irrelevant reasons. Like, the pressure
didn't come up in the first place
because of circumstances, because of
whatever. But um
the the the point of the faculty that
you're training is that your shame is
stronger than
the pressure for you to act
unwholesomely. So,
So,
it should be proportional to the worse
the misbehavior is and the more persistent
misbehavior is and the more persistent
it is, the more ashamed you feel. And uh
And uh
it's you really can't
um
force it or speed it up any more than
that because that's where you would go
wrong. You would think like um
essentially you would do things still
rooted in avoiding the discomfort.
And that's what would fail to teach the
mind a lesson of I shouldn't do this.
But if you stay with that discomfort of
um
that failure,
then well, even if you keep failing, at least
well, even if you keep failing, at least
it's sinking in
that this is bad. So,
So,
in other words, the
the shame
that accompanies
acting out of unwholesome intentions
will be
more painful than the pain of the
pressure. >> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> If you don't abandon the the
the reasoning, the faith, and the
reasoning, the faith, and the
the reasons why you were trying to
restrain yourself to begin with,
then the more you fail, the clearer it
becomes uh or or the clearer the
uh or or the clearer the
the failure becomes. Like, you you start
to see or make the connection
of why you shouldn't have been doing
this to begin with. And you you can't
expect it to be
uh an overnight change. It would be good
if it were, but um
you have to take into account that
the failure will keep happening, but the
growth comes
not from the amount of times you didn't
fail. The growth is the growth of the sense of
The growth is the growth of the sense of
shame.
So, you you can't uh
take that out of the picture and then
expect to still be making progress just
because externally you are
technically not failing now.
That's the wrong order where you think
like it's worse to have a determination
and to fail.
And like that naturally that feels bad,
but the thing is that's that the measure
is not how many times you fail in and of
itself, it's how much of that sense of
shame growing.
Perception of danger growing.
>> And if my like if I fail, I make
mistakes, and my mind
keeps pressuring me into the directions
of making basically the same mistakes
again, it's a sign of
it's a sign of
that it hasn't really understood whereas
when it would actually
stay with that sense of shame more,
it would be a sign that it actually
gets the message more.
>> Yeah, if if the
danger stands out over the benefit,
then you won't want to do it. But that's
not going to happen
um
if you just
look away from the problem, look away
from the fact that you still might give
in
by sort of yeah, tweaking the
circumstances or or just doing things in
order to avoid
the failure as a goal in itself.
You have to
think more in terms of the failure is
when I fail and I don't maintain the
sense of shame.
That's the much worse type of failure.
Well, either with like even if you don't
fail the the it's actually worse
if you \ \ succeed
not doing certain actions externally,
but you don't have a sense of shame
than if you do fail and and you give in,
but you
maintain a sense of shame.
Because letting go of the sense of shame, or you
letting go of the sense of shame, or you
could call it the perception of danger,
is delusion.
And delusion is worse than greed or
aversion. It's the worst of the three
defilements. It's a wrong view. You
could also say it's a wrong view.
When the Buddha said the worst of all
blameworthy thing is wrong view.
So, wrong view comes hand in hand with
you having done something unwholesome,
having done something against the
precepts, and not experiencing it as an
issue. And that is the worst of all blameworthy
And that is the worst of all blameworthy
things, far worse than somebody who did
the bad thing, but to the to that to the
extent of its badness, feels remorseful.
So, that's why the
um
shame and remorse are the first two or
the second and third faculty of a noble
disciple.
>> So, this is well way in the suttas when
people come to the Buddha and
confess their shortcomings to him, and
sometimes even pretty grave things.
He would actually say to them that
that's a progress, kind of
yeah, having the sense of shame and
regret is a good
>> say like, well,
not having transgressions is
um in itself growth in the noble's
discipline, because he also gave the
simile where he
uh one one ascetic that he met had this
view that
uh if somebody doesn't do bad actions by
body, speech, and mind,
then they are
they can be declared as a pure and uh
accomplished ascetic.
And then the Buddha said, if that was
the case, then a child, newborn child,
that doesn't even have the ability to do
anything bad, except from whimpering and
and eating,
that they would then they would be an
accomplished ascetic, like pure.
So,
that's that just goes to show again that
a sense of shame
like it's similar to the noble eightfold
path, it's the view
that certain things are unwholesome, but
that leads to the right speech and the
right action.
Not the right action just done in and of
itself in a isolated context,
which could be accidental.
It's the combination of
your perspective that says this is
unwholesome together with the abstinence
together with the abstinence
that makes the abstinence wear away
craving. Abstinence by itself, without the
Abstinence by itself, without the
perception of non-abstinence being
unwholesome, without that avenue being
closed, is just like a child.
That would be similar to just make
turning yourself
like an extreme version of that would be
turning yourself into a vegetable.
And then you wouldn't do anything bad.
But you it's not the doing the the
non-doing of anything bad is not
happening because you actually developed
that perception of
unwholesomeness.